<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: development | softr.li]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/categories/development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.softr.li/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-11T11:37:13+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.softr.li/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Romain Champourlier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[XCode failing when building for archiving because of a missing library link]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/06/11/xcode-failing-when-building-for-archiving-because-of-a-missing-library-link/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-11T11:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/06/11/xcode-failing-when-building-for-archiving-because-of-a-missing-library-link</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The issue</h3>

<p>You may be using opensource libraries within your iOS project. (<em>If you don't, you should, it's a great time-saver. Check <a href="http://pinterest.com/rchampourlier/best-ios-controls/">here</a> for some starters.</em>)</p>

<p>As you may know, XCode may sometimes become really painful when dealing with the <strong>compilation and linking of external libraries</strong>. It may just work fine when compiling for development, but when you want it compiled for distribution, XCode may just not agree anymore.</p>

<p>I just faced such an issue this morning. This time, I met the <code>ld: library not found for...</code> error:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2012-06-11-screenshot-1.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Googling a little, I found these two StackOverflow answers, but they could not help me. You can give a try, this may still contain the answer to your own issue.</p>

<h3>The solution</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/5584317/compile-build-or-archive-problems-with-xcode-4-and-dependancies">Compile, Build or Archive problems with Xcode 4 (and dependancies)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/6004919/missing-library-link-error-when-doing-product-build-for-archiving-in-xcode-4">Missing Library link error when doing Product > Build For Archiving in Xcode 4</a></li>
</ul>


<p>I checked where the generated could be, and looking at the logs of the build process, I could find the directory's path: <code>/Users/me/Library/Developer/Xcode/DerivedData/.../</code></p>

<p>Checking the content of this directory, I discovered that my issue was that the library was indeed not build for the <code>Distribution-iphoneos</code> configuration:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2012-06-11-screenshot-2.png"></p>

<p>Correcting the issue was as simple as going to the library's project settings and adding the <code>Distribution</code> configuration:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2012-06-11-screenshot-3.png"></p>

<h3>The conclusion</h3>

<p>Be sure to check that the libraries you include within your XCode project have all the necessary configurations setup!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to use Bootstrap within your Rails 3.1+ app]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/06/07/how-to-use-bootstrap-within-your-rails-3.1-app/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-07T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/06/07/how-to-use-bootstrap-within-your-rails-3.1-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap">Bootstrap</a> is a real gift from Twitter. It provides a good deal of packaged, well-designed and simple to use UI components for any web application.</p>

<p>I wanted to use it for quite some time, but I hadn't found the time nor the project to apply it on. I recently updated an administration web-app for one of my project, and I felt it was the good time.</p>

<p>So here are my first feedbacks and tips on how to integrated Bootstrap with Rails (I'm on Rails 3.2.5, it's the lowest-effort path if you're using Formtastic too).</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>First, where do I put the files?</h3>

<p>Say you want to use <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap">Twitter Bootstrap</a> within your Rails 3.1+ (ie. asset pipeline featured) application.</p>

<p>After some tests I couldn't find a simple way to <strong>keep the whole bootstrap directory packaged and get it accessed correctly by the asset pipeline</strong>. So the best way I found yet is to <strong>explode it into the appropriate directories</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>CSS files goes into <code>vendor/assets/stylesheets</code></li>
<li>JS files goes into <code>vendor/assets/javascripts</code></li>
<li>image files goes into <code>vendor/assets/images</code></li>
</ul>


<p>So this way I can simply require Bootstrap CSS through this <code>application.css</code> file:</p>

<p><code>css app/assets/application.css
/*
 * This is a manifest file that'll automatically include all the stylesheets available in this directory
 * and any sub-directories. You're free to add application-wide styles to this file and they'll appear at
 * the top of the compiled file, but it's generally better to create a new file per style scope.
 *= require_self
 *= require_tree .
 *= require bootstrap
*/
</code></p>

<p>If this does not work, be sure to <strong>restart your development server</strong> as changing location of assets may not be taken into account until restart...</p>

<h3>This breaks my tasty forms!</h3>

<p>Are you using <a href="https://github.com/justinfrench/formtastic">Formtastic</a>? I am, this is one of the things I like to have with every Rails project. However, Formtastic and Bootstrap do not naturally go together well.</p>

<p>To make them love each other, we have to add a gem which will tweak the way Formtastic builds the forms to make them Bootstrap-proof. This is the intent of <a href="https://github.com/rchampourlier/formtastic-bootstrap">formtastic-bootstrap</a>.</p>

<p>You can add this to your Gemfile, that should be all:</p>

<p><code>
gem 'formtastic-bootstrap', :git =&gt; 'https://github.com/rchampourlier/formtastic-bootstrap.git', :branch =&gt; 'bootstrap2-rails3-2-formtastic-2-2-1'
</code>
<em>This assumes your on Rails 3.2 and Formtastic 2.2.1, as the branch name indicates.</em></p>

<p>I've sent you to my own fork which is forking an already long chain of forks. The <a href="https://github.com/mjbellantoni/formtastic-bootstrap">original repo</a> seems not to be maintained anymore. My fork provides a <code>bootstrap2-rails3-2-formtastic-2-2-1</code> branch which should work for Rails 3.2 and the current version of Formtastic, the 2.2.1 (some changes were to be taken into account from 2.2.0).</p>

<p><em>My fork does not take all 2.2.1 changes into account. You may have issues with <code>time_select</code> inputs...</em></p>

<h3>My flash messages aren't that nice!</h3>

<p>To style your Rails' flash messages using the nice Bootstrap's alert style, you can have a look to this <a href="https://gist.github.com/2887844">gist</a>:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/2887844.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code>- if flash
  - flash.each do |level, message|
    %div{:class =&gt; &quot;alert #{flash_level(level)}&quot;}
      %button.close{:&quot;data-dismiss&quot; =&gt; 'alert'}= &quot;×&quot;
      = message</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>Just replace your current way of displaying the flashes in your template with this, and you're done!</p>

<p><code>ruby
= render :partial =&gt; 'layouts/flash', :locals =&gt; { :flash =&gt; flash }
</code></p>

<hr />

<p><em>I hope this helps, do not hesitate if you see mistakes or some parts which require additional details!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AppleScript to automate the setup of your development space]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/26/applescript-to-automate-the-setup-of-your-development-space/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-26T16:34:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/26/applescript-to-automate-the-setup-of-your-development-space</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is Saturday, and like every week-end, I'm getting a little lazy.</p>

<p>Say you're working on a Rails project on MacOS X. If you're like me, you like to have a terminal window for your project with several tabs:</p>

<ul>
<li>one for typing various commands,</li>
<li>one with your <code>spork</code> process,</li>
<li>one with your <code>rails console</code>,</li>
<li>and one with your <code>rails server</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Starting all this little world already involves some keystrokes and typing, even more if you're using Vagrant (which <a href="http://www.softr.li/blog/categories/vagrant/">I'm using for a week</a> and is really awesome).</p>

<p>So why not use the simple tools provided by Apple to have this setup with a single action?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The AppleScript</h2>

<p>AppleScript is the scripting solution provided by Apple and it's perfect for what we want to do. It's quite simple, and it allows you to script the Terminal application.</p>

<p>Here is the script:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/2794125.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code>-- This script enables you to use MacOS X AppleScript to open a terminal
-- window and several tabs to:
--   - load a vagrant box with vagrant up
--   - ssh in the box on each tab
--   - run specific commands within the vagrant box on different tabs
--
-- For example, open 4 tabs, each within the vagrant box, one with spork,
-- one with a Rails console and the last one with the rails server.
--
-- It assumes when you ssh into the vagrant box you automatically cd into
-- the project's directory (by having a `cd /vagrant` within your
-- `~/.bashrc` on the box for example).
--
-- It also uses a `dev-project` alias on the host which cd in the appropriate
-- project's directory, but you can just replace it by a `cd ...` command.

using terms from application &quot;Terminal&quot;
  tell application &quot;Terminal&quot;
    activate
    
    -- open the terminal's window, set its dimensions   
    set tab1 to do script
    do script &quot;dev-project&quot; in tab1
    do script &quot;vagrant up&quot; in tab1
    repeat
      delay 0.5
      if busy of tab1 is false then exit repeat
    end repeat
    
    -- tab 1: ssh in vagrant
    do script &quot;vagrant ssh&quot; in tab1
    delay 0.5
    
    -- tab 2: ssh in vagrant and run spork
    tell application &quot;System Events&quot; to keystroke &quot;t&quot; using command down &amp; return
    set tab2 to tab 2 of currentWindow
    do script &quot;dev-project&quot; in tab2
    do script &quot;vagrant ssh&quot; in tab2
    do script &quot;bundle exec spork&quot; in tab2
    delay 0.5
    
    -- tab 3: ssh in vagrant and run rails console
    tell application &quot;System Events&quot; to keystroke &quot;t&quot; using command down &amp; return
    set tab3 to tab 3 of currentWindow
    do script &quot;dev-project&quot; in tab3
    do script &quot;vagrant ssh&quot; in tab3
    do script &quot;bundle exec rails console&quot; in tab3
    delay 0.5
    
    -- tab 4: ssh in vagrant and run spork
    tell application &quot;System Events&quot; to keystroke &quot;t&quot; using command down &amp; return
    set tab4 to tab 4 of currentWindow
    do script &quot;dev-project&quot; in tab4
    do script &quot;vagrant ssh&quot; in tab4
    do script &quot;bundle exec rails server&quot; in tab4
  end tell
end using terms from</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>It's intended for my use, so it relies on some aliases I've defined on my host machine. But it's quite simple to read and comes with some comments, so I'm sure you will have no difficulty to adapt it to your needs.</p>

<h2>Access the script</h2>

<p>You can run this script from a Terminal window by using <code>osascript path/to/the/script.scpt</code>, but I prefer to have it in the script menu.</p>

<p>You can activate the script menu from the script editor's preferences. Then just have a look in the menu to open the user's scripts directory and put your script file in it.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>If you need any help, just ask!</em></p>

<p><em>If you're aware of a better solution to setup a development environment like this, don't hesitate to tell me! I'm pretty sure there are some other ways I don't know yet...</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Forked TabBarKit]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/24/forked-tabbarkit/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-24T16:52:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/24/forked-tabbarkit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have had to rewrite some parts of TBKTabBarController since I needed to be able to programmatically select a tab. This is normally possible by setting the <code>selectedIndex</code> or the <code>selectedViewController</code> property of the tab bar controller, but this was not working with TabBarKit.</p>

<p>I investigated and detected this behavior was not implemented, so I decided to complete it myself.</p>

<p>Along the way, I discovered there were some issues with the <code>containerView</code> being mixed up with the <code>TBKTabBarController</code>'s view, so I also corrected these bugs.</p>

<p>I've forked the repository and updated it with my corrected code, so have a look to this <a href="https://github.com/rchampourlier/TabBarKit">repo</a> if you need this.</p>

<p>Oh, I also added a <code>TBKTabBarStyleTwiceHeight</code> I use to double the size of the tab bar on iPad, so you get this for free too ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[vagrant-stacks, a provision-on-demand tool for Vagrant!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/20/vagrant-stacks-a-provision-on-demand-tool-for-vagrant/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-20T09:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/20/vagrant-stacks-a-provision-on-demand-tool-for-vagrant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.vagrantup.com">Vagrant</a> is really an excellent tool for building and using virtual machines for your development environment. It <strong>ease the maintenance</strong> and allows to <strong>share the same environment within the whole team</strong>.</p>

<p>However, <strong>Vagrant itself only provides you with barebones boxes</strong>.  You still have to work for provisioning the box, <strong>which requires that you build a Chef recipe</strong> (or Puppet, but I'm using Chef so I will only refer to this one).</p>

<p><strong>Instead of using a packaged box</strong> (e.g. from <a href="[http://vagrantbox.es">vagrantbox.es</a>) which you may <strong>not trust or feal comfortable with</strong>, you can use <a href="https://github.com/rchampourlier/vagrant-stacks">this repo</a> to <strong>build and package your Vagrant box by yourself</strong>. It provides the tools and some configurations which will enable you to build a provisioned box without writing the recipe! The advantage of this approach over packaged boxes is that you can <strong>review how the box is built and provisioned</strong>. You can even refine the configurations and build new ones by forking the repo and submitting pull requests!</p>

<p>It already provides a configuration for a <strong>Ruby 1.9.2-p290 stack, managed with rbenv and Bundler, plus a PostgreSQL 8.4 database and MongoDB</strong>.</p>

<p>So feel free to <strong>try and share new configurations</strong>! Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
