<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: notetomyself | softr.li]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/categories/notetomyself/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.softr.li/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-21T11:54:14+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.softr.li/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Romain Champourlier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manually installing a gem from a git repo]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/04/22/manually-installing-a-gem-from-a-git-repo/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-22T10:16:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/04/22/manually-installing-a-gem-from-a-git-repo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>
gem uninstall gem_name
git clone git://github.com/repo_name/gem_name.git
cd gem_name
gem build gem_name.gemspec
gem install ./&lt;the gem that was compiled&gt;
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Linking local node modules with npm]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/04/16/linking-local-node-modules-with-npm/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-16T10:10:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/04/16/linking-local-node-modules-with-npm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How to link a <strong>node module</strong> to a <strong>local source directory</strong> instead of installing from npm repository.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Link a module to a local repo</h2>

<p>When you need a fresher version of a module that the one published to npm repository (e.g. if you have your own patch, if new commits haven't been released yet), you may want to clone the module locally and have npm use it instead of the published one.</p>

<p>To do this, you <strong>link</strong> your local package.</p>

<pre><code>git clone https://github.com/repo/node-module.git
cd node-module
npm link
</code></pre>

<p><em>You may need to <code>sudo</code> to perform the <code>link</code> command (this is because the link gets installed system-wide, in <code>/usr/local/lib/node_modules</code> on my MacOS X system).</em></p>

<p><strong>Check the log of this command to see on which path npm references the linked module. In my case, the module was named as <code>node-module</code>, but npm was using <code>module</code> for the reference. In this case, be sure to link in your app (next section) using <code>module</code> and not <code>node-module</code>.</strong></p>

<h2>Link this module in your node application</h2>

<p>You will now tell npm to use this linked version of the module for your application:</p>

<pre><code>cd your_application
npm link module
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using cloned virtualized machines but having issues with your network configuration?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/01/05/using-cloned-virtualized-machines-but-having-issues-with-your-network-configuration/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-05T09:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/01/05/using-cloned-virtualized-machines-but-having-issues-with-your-network-configuration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trying to get your cloned VirtualBox on the host network without success? This may help you...</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>If like me, you're using <strong>VirtualBox virtual machines</strong> a lot, eg.:</p>

<ul>
<li>to <strong>simulate your production environment</strong> (what we may call <em>staging</em>),</li>
<li>or more lately in my case, to <strong>run a PostgreSQL database</strong> and thus stop using SQLite to do your Rails developments and just use the production's server...</li>
</ul>


<p>...then you may have wanted to clone some of your virtual machines once you installed the barebone server, and you may thus have faced <strong>an issue with the network of the cloned machine not working anymore.</strong></p>

<p><strong>The solution to the problem is quite simple, but it needs to be found!</strong></p>

<p>This one is working well with my images under <strong> Ubuntu 10.04.3 LTS</strong>. You can find some help <a href="http://blog.computerant.com/2010/01/02/virtualbox-cloning-ubuntu/">on this other post</a>, or if you want the shortest way:</p>

<p><code>
sudo mv /etc/udev/rules.d/70-persistent-net.rules /etc/udev/rules.d/70-persistent-net.rules.broken
sudo shutdown now -r
</code></p>

<p>This should restart your machine... and restore your network! Have fun ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
