<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ios | softr.li]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/categories/ios/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.softr.li/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-07T12:17:20+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.softr.li/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Romain Champourlier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Forked TabBarKit]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/24/forked-tabbarkit/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-24T16:52:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/24/forked-tabbarkit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have had to rewrite some parts of TBKTabBarController since I needed to be able to programmatically select a tab. This is normally possible by setting the <code>selectedIndex</code> or the <code>selectedViewController</code> property of the tab bar controller, but this was not working with TabBarKit.</p>

<p>I investigated and detected this behavior was not implemented, so I decided to complete it myself.</p>

<p>Along the way, I discovered there were some issues with the <code>containerView</code> being mixed up with the <code>TBKTabBarController</code>'s view, so I also corrected these bugs.</p>

<p>I've forked the repository and updated it with my corrected code, so have a look to this <a href="https://github.com/rchampourlier/TabBarKit">repo</a> if you need this.</p>

<p>Oh, I also added a <code>TBKTabBarStyleTwiceHeight</code> I use to double the size of the tab bar on iPad, so you get this for free too ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Debugging TabBarKit, a barebones kit for custom tab bar on iOS]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/10/debugging-tabbarkit-a-barebones-kit-for-custom-tab-bar-on-ios/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-10T12:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/05/10/debugging-tabbarkit-a-barebones-kit-for-custom-tab-bar-on-ios</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For our <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/fr/app/cultimots-un-jeu-culture-vocabulaire/id483710651?l=fr&amp;ls=1&amp;mt=8">Cultimots</a> application, I wanted to customize the application's tab bar. I looked a little on Google, <a href="http://cocoacontrols.com/">cocoacontrols.com</a>, Github, but I didn't want to use a full-featured solution which may not remain configurable for what I add in mind.</p>

<p>I finally went for <strong>TabBarKit</strong>, which is quite barebones, <strong>reproducing the basic features of <code>UITabBar</code></strong> while letting me <strong>play with the code to get my own thing</strong>.</p>

<p>On this way I encountered several time-consuming issues due to the non-existent documentation of TabBarKit and some bugs in the shared code. Since I already customized the code to fit my own project <strong>I won't share the updated source code</strong>, I will however share the issues I met and the solutions I found. Hope this will make your path faster than mine!</p>

<!--more -->


<h3>Confusion between tab bar style and tab bar item selection style</h3>

<p>There is a confusion between the tab bar's style, which is a <code>TBKTabBarStyle</code>, and the tab bar item selection's style, which is a <code>TBKTabBarItemSelectionStyle</code>.</p>

<p>This confusion is explicit in these lines:</p>

<p><code>objc TabBarKit/Classes/TBKTabBarController.m:119
TBKTabBarItem *tabItem = [[[TBKTabBarItem alloc] initWithImageName:controller.tabImageName style:self.tabBarStyle tag:tagIndex title:controller.title] autorelease];
</code></p>

<p><code>objc TabBarKit/Classes/TBKTabBarItem.m:170
-(id) initWithImageName:(NSString *)anImageName style:(TBKTabBarItemSelectionStyle)aStyle tag:(NSInteger)aTag title:(NSString *)aTitle {
</code></p>

<p>The tab bar item <code>init</code> method expects <code>aStyle</code> to be a <code>TBKTabBarItemSelectionStyle</code> but the controller provides its own style, which is a <code>TBKTabBarStyle</code>. This is OK in the source code because in fact the both style are <code>enum</code>s with matching integer values. If you add yours, just be sure to clean this mess.</p>

<h2>Enabling titles</h2>

<p>In the source code from the Github repo, titles are disabled. To restore them, you will have to uncomment some lines from <code>TabBarKit/Classes/TBKTabBarItem.m</code>:</p>

<p><code>``objc TabBarKit/Classes/TBKTabBarItem.m:178-188</code>
if (self.controllerTitle &amp;&amp; self.selectionStyle == TBKTabBarItemDefaultSelectionStyle) {</p>

<pre><code>    /*
    self.displayTitle = YES;
    self.titleLabel.font = [UIFont boldSystemFontOfSize:10.0];
    self.titleLabel.textAlignment = UITextAlignmentCenter;
    self.titleLabel.contentMode = UIViewContentModeLeft;
    self.imageEdgeInsets = UIEdgeInsetsMake(0, 22, 11, 0);
    self.titleEdgeInsets = UIEdgeInsetsMake(0, -35, 2, 0);
    [self setTitle:self.controllerTitle forState:(UIControlStateNormal | UIControlStateSelected)];
    */
}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>There is also a bug on this line:</p>

<p><code>objc TabBarKit/Classes/TBKTabBarItem.m:186
[self setTitle:self.controllerTitle forState:(UIControlStateNormal | UIControlStateSelected)];
</code></p>

<p>If you set the title for both <code>UIControlStateNormal</code> and <code>UIControlStateSelected</code>, it won't show up for the tab bar items which are not selected, and their layout will get broken. Just replace the line by this:</p>

<p><code>objc TabBarKit/Classes/TBKTabBarItem.m:186
[self setTitle:self.controllerTitle forState:(UIControlStateNormal)];
</code></p>

<h2>Finishing touch</h2>

<h3>Grey titles for the non-selected items</h3>

<p>Update the lines 170 to 175 to have this in <code>TabBarKit/Classes/TBKTabBar.m</code>:</p>

<p>```objc TabBarKit/Classes/TBKTabBar.m:170-175
for (TBKTabBarItem *tab in self.items) {</p>

<pre><code>currentBounds.origin.x += self.tabMargin;
tab.frame = currentBounds;
currentBounds.origin.x += currentBounds.size.width;
[self addSubview:tab];
tab.titleLabel.textColor = [UIColor grayColor]; // added line
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Update the <code>setSelected:</code> method in <code>TabBarKit/Classes/TBKTabBarItem.m:213-217</code>:</p>

<p>```objc</p>

<pre><code>else {
    if ([self.layer.sublayers containsObject:self.selectionLayer]) {
        [self.selectionLayer removeFromSuperlayer];
    }
self.titleLabel.textColor = [UIColor grayColor]; // added line
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p><strong>Your tab bar should already look great! The rest is customization, and it's up to you! Have fun!</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting the correct object data model for really automatic CoreData lightweight migrations]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/01/17/getting-the-correct-object-data-model-for-really-automatic-coredata-lightweight-migration/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-17T09:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2012/01/17/getting-the-correct-object-data-model-for-really-automatic-coredata-lightweight-migration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you're using CoreData for your iOS application, you may have the need sometimes <strong>to update your data model</strong>. If your application is already live (e.g. shipped on the AppStore), you will have to <strong>migrate your existing data when updating the model</strong>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Lightweight migration</h2>

<p>As long as your migration is not too complicated, <strong>CoreData provides a simple way to do this</strong>, using what they call the <strong>lightweight migration process</strong>. This process is not-that-bad documented in Apple documentation's <em>(ref 1)</em>, but... there is a piece of code lacking, and making the whole thing "automatic" was not so easy...</p>

<h2>Automatic migration</h2>

<p>The automatic-nature of the process is given by the creation of a new version of your Data Model in XCode, and telling it which version is the current one (see <em>ref 2</em> for Apple's documentation on this matter).</p>

<p>Now that you've created your second version, you may want to use documentation's code sample to build your lightweight migration process:</p>

<p>``` objc
NSError <em>error;
NSURL </em>storeURL = &lt;#The URL of a persistent store#>;
NSPersistentStoreCoordinator <em>psc = &lt;#The coordinator#>;
NSDictionary </em>options = [NSDictionary dictionaryWithObjectsAndKeys:</p>

<pre><code>[NSNumber numberWithBool:YES], NSMigratePersistentStoresAutomaticallyOption,
[NSNumber numberWithBool:YES], NSInferMappingModelAutomaticallyOption, nil];
</code></pre>

<p>if (![psc addPersistentStoreWithType:&lt;#Store type#> configuration:&lt;#Configuration or nil#> URL:storeURL options:options error:&amp;error]) {
  // Handle the error.
}
```</p>

<p>At this stage, most of us already have a way of getting the <code>NSManagedObjectModel</code> instance required to build a <code>NSPersistentCoordinator</code> instance. This generally involves this code (often put in the application's delegate):</p>

<p>``` objc
- (NSManagedObjectModel *)managedObjectModel {
  if (managedObjectModel != nil) {</p>

<pre><code>return managedObjectModel;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  managedObjectModel = [[NSManagedObjectModel mergedModelFromBundles:nil] retain];
  return managedObjectModel;
}
```</p>

<p>The issue with this is that you're gonna get a "<code>Can't merge models with two different entities named 'EntityName'</code>" exception, because you're in fact merging the two versions of your model... <strong>And here broke the automaticity!</strong></p>

<p>You indeed can't merge your two model versions. What you want is your current model version to get loaded into the <code>NSPersistentStoreCoordinator</code>. Here you have two choices:</p>

<ol>
<li>Everything I could find on the web was giving me a solution requiring to manually enter the name of the new model version so that I could load the correct model version. But hey! I'm telling XCode what the current version is, shouldn't it be enough?</li>
<li>Your second solution, the truly automatic one is here, just one line away...</li>
</ol>


<p><code>objc Load the current NSManagedObjectModel using XCode generated VersionInfo property list
- (NSManagedObjectModel *)currentManagedObjectModel {
  // Find and open the .plist file with the current version name
  // Path to the plist (in the application bundle)
  NSString *pathToDataModelVersionInfoPlist = [[NSBundle mainBundle] pathForResource:@"VersionInfo" ofType:@"plist" inDirectory:@"DataModel.momd"];
  NSDictionary *dataModelVersionInfo = [[NSDictionary alloc] initWithContentsOfFile:pathToDataModelVersionInfoPlist];
  NSString *currentModelName = [dataModelVersionInfo objectForKey:@"NSManagedObjectModel_CurrentVersionName"];
  NSString *modelPath = [[NSBundle mainBundle] pathForResource:currentModelName ofType:@"mom" inDirectory:@"DataModel.momd"];
  NSURL *modelURL = [NSURL fileURLWithPath:modelPath];
  return [[[NSManagedObjectModel alloc] initWithContentsOfURL:modelURL] autorelease];
}
</code></p>

<p>With this small piece of code, you will read the <code>VersionInfo.plist</code> file maintained by XCode which contains the reference to the current data model. So now, each time you set a new data model version, it will get chosen automatically and migrated without having to update you code!</p>

<p><strong>NB: This has not been tested a lot.</strong> It works with iOS 5 and should be tested on different versions before releasing any code using this trick. It is dependent on a file built and added to the bundle by XCode, so you may have to check with updates that it is not changed or removed.</p>

<h2>iOS documentation references</h2>

<ol>
<li>iOS x.x Library > Data Management > Core Data Model Versioning and Data Migration Programming Guide > Lightweight Migration</li>
<li>iOS x.x Library > Data Management > Core Data Model Versioning and Data Migration Programming Guide > Versioning > Model Versions</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working with custom table view cells defined in NIB files]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.softr.li/blog/2011/09/14/working-with-custom-table-view-cells-defined-in-nib-files/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-14T08:59:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.softr.li/blog/2011/09/14/working-with-custom-table-view-cells-defined-in-nib-files</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you're using custom table view cells defined within NIB/XIB files for your iOS application, and you're a beginner like me, you may do one of these two mistakes. Just find out what not to do by having a look at this article!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<h2>Context</h2>

<p>One of the projects I'm currently working on involves displaying custom UITableViewCells. To be exact, I display a dynamic list of elements which can be either displayed by a <code>UITableViewCell</code> <strong>A</strong> or a <code>UITableViewCell</code> <strong>B</strong>. Each of these cells is defined in its own NIB file.</p>

<ul>
<li>Cell A has 3 subviews: 2 labels and a progress view.</li>
<li>Cell B has only 1 subview, the label.</li>
</ul>


<h2>My first mistake was to try using IBOutlets to update the cell's content.</h2>

<p>I have a subclass of <code>UITableViewController</code> which will load the cells' NIB files when needed (from <code>UITableViewCell *)tableView:(UITableView *)tableView cellForRowAtIndexPath:(NSIndexPath *)indexPath</code> - you can have a look at the "A Closer Look at Table-View Cells" documentation page for more information).</p>

<p>In the cell's NIB, I have set the File's Owner as my subclass of <code>UITableViewController</code>. I setup an outlet to link to the cell so I have a reference when I load it in my table view controller. However <strong>I also wanted to use IBOutlets to link to the cell's subviews... This is a bad idea.</strong> This lead to some bizarre side-effects when displaying the table view, such as some rows replacing others when scrolling.</p>

<p>If you have subviews in your custom cell you want to update (if you don't, I'm not sure I understand how you're using your cells...), <strong>follow the documentation and use the tag value of your subviews when editing the NIB file</strong>. From your controller, you can access them with <code>[cell viewForTag:(NSInteger)tag]</code>.</p>

<h2>My second mistake was to use '0' as a tag.</h2>

<p>One last thing. Even if I did not read it in the documentation, maybe <strong>you should not use '0' as a tag</strong>. I was using it for one of my subview and only the subview tagged '0' was displayed, the other disappeared. So just change the tag from the default value, and start with '1'.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
